this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
PC radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society software Magazine
online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
I'm your host brijesh amanat and today
my guest is on freund
on his years of experience in helping
developers master the skills needed to
advance in the career one is passionate
about creating new ways for developers
to level up he's co-founder and CEO of
Wilco a free upscaling platform for
developers prior to that he was VP
product and VP engineering at Weber and
VP engineering at Handy on is also an
angel investor and advisor to startups
on welcome to software engineering radio
is there anything I missed in your bio
that you'd like to add thanks so much no
I think you pretty much covered all of
the professional aspects I'd say I'm
also an amateur drummer
excellent thank you as the field of
technology is constantly evolving it's
crucial for engineers to stay current
with the latest tools and Technologies
we will be talking today about
upskilling on how developers need to
keep learning upskilling and reskilling
throughout their career we have covered
learning previously in episodes 543
episode 529 524 515 and 491. I'll make
sure we link to these in the show notes
let's start with the basics so from my
perspective when I look at upskilling or
their closest other term that comes to
mind is reskilling which is you know I
have an employee or team member that I'm
going to train to teach him or her to do
something else
what is upscaling in that context is it
same
well it is very similar you know those
two terms do have a relation with each
other but for me reskilling is the act
of taking someone who's skilled at one
thing and making them scaled at
something else and those two things
could be completely independent so for
example maybe I'm a salesperson and I'm
going through a reskilling program to
make me a good marketer for example so
that would be reskilling upskilling is I
have a specific skill set and I'm taking
the steps needed to ensure that I become
better in that skill set so for example
I could be a marketer but I have some
gaps in my knowledge in various areas
maybe I'm only focused on PPC but I
haven't learned anything having to do
with brand marketing so I pick up brand
marketing and to me that is a sort of
upskill so these were the examples
outside of engineering when we talk
about engineering the terms could be a
bit more blur because if I'm a full
stack developer and I'm going through a
process that turns me into a mobile
developer is that considered reskilling
or upskilling I can't say that I have a
good answer for that but I would say
that as long as you're within the realm
of software engineering I would call it
upscaling yep that makes sense so if
you're going deeper or increasing the
breadth of your skills that would be
upskilling whereas learning something
completely new would be reskilling
exactly right you've also mentioned or
talked previously about leveling up what
does that term mean yeah so leveling up
unlike upskilling and reskilling that
sort of became industry terms leveling
up is a bit more informal and to me
leveling up is you know if you're at a
certain level and and I don't want to
put names you know some people might say
junior engineer senior engineer if you
have a career ladder you might add
titles such as staff engineer or
principal engineer and you you could say
that you know switching from one of
these levels to another is leveling up
but I like to look at it as more
holistic you're at a certain level it
doesn't have to have a very clear and
concise definition but you're at a
certain level and you've picked up
skills and you feel like you're ready
for more advanced stuff so you might
from a title perspective level up every
few years but if you encountered
something challenging let's say that for
the first time you have to deal with
something in production to me that
experience becomes a step function in
your growth and once you've completed
that in a way you've leveled up right so
it's basically gaining experience and as
you gain experience to become more
confident in dealing with that problem
you know you're almost transitioned to
the next level exactly and it's not just
confidence by the way to me it's a
combination of throughout this
experience you've gained confidence
you've also gained more training for
your data set I would say so your
pattern matching becomes better next
time around and you've also perhaps
developed intuition as part of this
eventually the experience to me is the
combination of confidence intuition and
pattern matching right related to that
around professional development you have
any suggestions on how an engineer
should approach professional development
you know you've got to look at learning
new skills new abilities as you want to
progress in your career but is there a
mindful way one can approach
professional development it's a great
question and I think that first and
foremost I think it should absolutely be
the goal for every engineer in their
career we are in most of the engineers
I've met are very curious and using that
Curiosity to gain further skills I think
is one of the best ways we can do for
you know both for our career and and I
would say also for our well-being
because most of the developers I know
love development and it's not just a day
job to them they actually care about the
profession and want to become better at
what they do the thing is to become
better it's not necessarily just about
writing better code which is where I
think a lot of the people are getting it
wrong becoming a better engineer is a
combination of many soft and hard skills
that you need to pick up and you need to
find good ways to acquire them so I
would say the first thing in your
upscaling journey is to figure out where
you want to go and one of the nice
things you can do is when you're
starting out look around you and figure
out who are your role models and what
have they achieved that you would like
to achieve and then start setting more
specific goals on the way to get there
so for one person this could be I want
to become the top expert on topic X and
for another person that could be I want
to know a little about everything and
you know both of these are legitimate
goals and it varies by the character of
the person but first step in your
upscaling path just figure out where you
want to get what is your North Star and
then from then on we can talk about the
tactics to get there right and
throughout the session we will touch
into various tactics so the first step
is identify your North Star and then
work towards achieving that end State
yeah exactly thanks moving on to the
benefits of upskilling I like to dig a
bit deeper into that why has upskilling
become more relevant now
well one thing that is hard to ignore is
that technology keeps moving faster so
the derivative the rate of change is
becoming faster as well and when
everything is progressing and you're
staying in the same place you've
basically gone backwards so if you're
not taking the time to upscale your
skills are auditory ID you know I'm no
longer actively an engineer I've I've
switched over to management a few years
ago I think I was very skilled when I
was an engineer but then looking at the
world today there are so many skills
that I haven't acquired like I've never
dealt with kubernetes for example which
has become the de facto standard for so
many things these days right so staying
in place could be a problem and then
more specifically what's happening today
two main secular shifts in our industry
have a lot of impact one of them is the
Advent of low code and no code platforms
and the other is AI and you know
everyone's talking about chechi PD but
this could also be GitHub co-pilot or
tab9 the combination of these two things
mean that you as an engineer don't have
to focus as much on boilerplate as you
used to in the past so the grunt work
the simple stuff is taken care of by
machines and when I say simple stuff it
could still be very time consuming or
had been time consuming but is no longer
there and now Engineers really need to
focus on Advanced scenarios on decision
making on you know the places where
humans shine and getting the basics
right is just not enough anymore agreed
I think I'm in a similar state where the
technology landscape changes so quickly
the moment you step out of it for a you
know for a short period the entire
landscape changes and it's very
difficult to then catch on or you know
learn the new technologies exactly I
actually had to deal with that in the
past I kind of took a pause from
engineering and had other roles and then
then came back and I had to pick up
completely new technologies and we're
talking just 18 months and within those
18 months I had to pick up completely
new technologies methodologies it's
crazy how fast it's moving we as
Engineers just you know the good thing
is that if we have the basic skills
right we can pick up whatever change we
can pick it up quickly but we always
need to be at the top of our game I have
an entire section later on how
engineering managers function in the new
world and how they can support their
teams on upskilling so we'll come back
to that but continuing on the benefits
of upskilling what about the benefits
for the firm well first and foremost you
know if you look at research you see
that the number one motivator for
software Engineers is opportunities for
professional growth and you know there
are so many surveys done on this topic
and it's always the number one motivator
more than compensation or anything else
the second thing is and it's kind of the
flip side if you look at why people are
leaving so there is a McKinsey research
on why people are leaving their jobs and
you see that the number one reason is
lack of opportunities for professional
growth so if not for anything else I
would say if you want to retain your top
talent make sure that you invest in
their skills the second thing there's a
really cool comic strip that I like that
it has like two managers speaking to
each other and one of them is saying
what if we invest in our people and they
leave
and the other one is saying well what if
we don't invest in them and they stay oh
obviously yeah the better skill the
people are the more productive they
become the less mistakes they make and
you know you can always just try to hire
more and more talent and more
experienced people but then sometimes
it's really a better approach to take
the existing people you have
and help them Bridge whatever experience
Gap they have yeah I've seen that comic
strip it's it's very what if we don't
upskill our employees in this day and it
just you know holds back the entire
company from progressing to the next
level
yeah the cost of someone who's not good
at what they do is disproportionately
large it's really something you want to
avoid in software engineering agreed
related to the benefits how important is
it for engineers to have a diverse skill
set
it's a really good question and it
relates to what I said earlier you know
some people really want to focus on one
thing and do it the best they can and
that's okay so you know if you were a
cobal programmer in 1999 then all of the
banks in the world wanted to get your
time and were willing to pay top dollar
for this and you know having a narrow
skill set actually worked in your favor
during those years especially if you're
an expert the reason I prefer to have a
more diverse skill set is hey because as
we mentioned earlier technology is
changing rapidly in a rapid skill set
allows you to evolve together with it
and two I think that a lot of what we're
experiencing in one stack or one domain
could be translated to another domain so
I mentioned earlier that 18 months
Hiatus from software engineering and
then coming back
I came back to something completely
different so the last thing I did before
that Hiatus was working on Windows
kernel device drivers the first thing I
did coming back was working on a Ruby on
Rails web back end now these two are
seemingly unrelated but a lot of the
skills I picked up in previous
iterations helped me bridge the gap
really quickly so I think a diverse
skill set is super important and then I
also think that there are a lot of
skills that are always needed and always
necessary so you know the ability to
communicate with your team members I
don't think anyone can live without that
one right and the ability to do it in a
respectful and efficient manner the
ability to take a problem and break it
down into smaller problems that's
definitely something you're going to
need in so many different domains so you
could say oh I only want to focus on
this specific language or the specific
platform or the specific type of
programming but even if you're doing
that I would say don't focus on a
specific skill you still need to pick up
all the skills that would allow you to
work efficiently right can you give me
an example how having a diverse skill
set has helped you in your career yeah
certainly so you know I'm gonna cheat a
bit and you know switch to places where
I was a manager but when you're a
manager you end up managing a large
engineering team and a large engineering
team by definition is going to have
different types of people so you're
going to have full stack web developers
and you're going to have database people
and you're going to have mobile
developers and front end and you know
basically anything and data and anything
you can come up with
and the ability to have a conversation
with each and every one of them an
informed conversation is just Priceless
now it doesn't mean that you need to go
speak to the database person and help
them develop queries that's not the
point but when they come to you with
ideas when they come to you with
requests for advice you want to be able
to have that conversation and I did that
as a manager but you know it could also
be for a staff engineer who spends a lot
of time mentoring others
and if the only thing they know how to
do is you know that specific area if all
they know is you know a specific type of
algorithm or a specific back-end
language and nothing else they're going
to have a really hard time mentoring
people around them who are trying to
pick up other skills
yep makes sense so what you're saying is
basically it helps you not only in
coaching and mentoring your team but
also helps as you progress in your
career to become an engineering manager
because you've got a wider view in terms
of the various things which happen in
the entire technology stack exactly and
if you're looking for a more tactical
example I would say I was working as a
full stack developer but actually it was
more back-end maintaining the backend
server and the company got Acquired and
one of the first thing that happened
post acquisition is I actually had to
deal with a production outage with the
product of the acquiring company which I
knew nothing about
and the system was basically grinding to
a halt and no one was able to deal with
it and everyone kept increasing so this
system had you know workers and everyone
kept increasing the number of workers to
deal with the heavy load the system was
experiencing and even though I knew
nothing about the system I did know a
thing or two about servers and back-end
systems and databases and I quickly was
able to figure out that it was actually
the database that was the bottleneck and
the right way to fix it is not
increasing the number of workers but
actually decreasing it so the database
can pick up and start processing things
in the normal time frame so you know
even though I knew nothing about their
server It Was Written in a language that
I wasn't proficient at it was a
production system I was not familiar
with the fact that I had a diverse skill
set enabled me to get into the situation
and understand what was happening and
then come up with a way to resolve it
it's a very good example we'll move on
to the next section in terms of looking
at ways to upskill Engineers need to
take the initiative to learn new skills
and improve their abilities in order to
advance in their careers what are the
various revenues available to developers
to upskill well the first thing I would
say which I think is the most important
thing is figure out who are the people
around you that you want to learn from
as much as it's unscalable software
engineering in many ways is still sort
of an apprenticeship model and you want
to find the best mentors around so that
is the first thing I would say and you
know the more people you have to learn
from the better because no one's perfect
and you want to synthesize what you're
seeing from various people to be able to
create your own career and your own
style so that is absolutely the number
one piece of advice I would give to
anyone wanting to upskill and the second
thing and this is assuming like we said
earlier that you've set your North Star
and you know where you want to get is
apart from the people around you figure
out the resources that you have in your
disposal and I think if you want to
maximize your learning you need to
combine two types of resources you need
something that's more theoretical that's
going to give you the knowledge and then
you need something that's more practical
or Hands-On that's going to give you the
skills or the wisdom and and on the
theoretical side this could be some sort
of course you know it could be at a
university it's going to be an online
course it doesn't really matter reading
a book and then on the more practical
side you could contribute to open source
projects you know even though they also
have their limitations but you can
contribute to open source projects you
can create your own side projects and
you can practice using dedicated tools
but definitely make sure that you're
mixing the theory and the practice one
of them is simply not enough
thanks so for summer is the first the
starting point should be people or
finding a mentor whom you can then work
closely with to understand the resources
available and when you look at resources
there are two types of resources
theoretical and practical and the
Practical ones ideally as you are the
open source contributions that you make
well I wouldn't say ideally open source
contributions I would say open source
contributions are one way of gaining
hands-on experience and it also has its
disadvantages so contributing to open
source is great but the workflow is
usually different than the type of
workflow you'll see within a company
you're most likely not maintaining a
production system for that open source
project there are a lot of a lot of
limitations to that so try to combine as
many ways of getting hands-on experience
as possible so that could be open source
contributions
side projects we can talk about willco
later that's another way to do that the
important thing is to mix various
techniques
all right
we have touched on mentorship I just
want to dig a bit deeper into that what
is the role of mentorship and networking
in professional development
so it's a great question because it's
actually you know a topic we could
probably talk for a full hour just about
that mentorship is a very complicated
complex and important relationship and
that's why picking your mentors is
really important and and these need to
be people that not only represent
what you want to achieve or where you're
striving to be but also people who are
able to create a good rapport with you
and are able to point you in the right
direction without judging but also
without micromanaging
a good Mentor is going to ask you
questions is going to dig deeper into
the various ways you're thinking of
tackling a problem so let's assume that
you're designing a new component and you
want to get some advice from your mentor
one way a mentor can deal with this is
say oh this is what I've done in the
past this is what you should be doing
now this is great if if the goal is to
impart knowledge but I think a better
Mentor is going to ask you well what are
the various ways that you're thinking
about what are the pros and cons that
you're seeing to each one of them now
they might add their own knowledge in
between you know you might say you come
up with a disadvantage of one of the
ways that you were considering and the
mentor might point out you know what
that is actually not a meaningful con
you know you shouldn't really be
spending too much time on this that's
okay in parting knowledge it is one of
the things that's required out of this
relationship but it really needs to be a
conversation where the mentor is
encouraging you to think and there are
not a lot of people who can do that
effectively so picking a good Mentor is
an art and Science in itself and it
could really change the trajectory of
your career here
if there are not many mentors or good
mentors out there any tips or
suggestions on how one can go about
finding and building relationships with
mentors
yeah you know first of all start with
thinking as we said earlier who are the
people that you want to be like and that
could be because they have a command of
some specific hard skill set but it also
could be because you see oh these are
people who are making everyone around
them work better right that's another
thing you might want to learn in your
career and by the way a very useful
skill so figuring out who are the people
that you should be learning from is the
first step the second step is and this
is a very tricky one is understanding if
you want your mentors to be from within
your team or outside the team and
there's no right or wrong answer here
and Mentor within your team has way
better context on the one hand but on
the other hand can seem as more biased
or you know at some point if they have a
say in your promotion it could be seen
by others as favoritism and things like
that so you know once again like I said
earlier you want to balance different
mentors so I would say pick a few
mentors both from within your team and
from outside the team and this is a
long-term relationship so before they
become your mentors they should really
have or you should really have a lot of
hours spent with them I mean this could
be through work this could be through
various other channels but you want to
spend a lot of time with them discussing
things and in a way at some point
they've become an unofficial mentor and
then it's up to you if you want to turn
this into something a bit more formal or
not I really have no opinion this way or
the other but definitely spend that
meaningful time with them beforehand
okay great to make it a bit more
concrete and if you don't mind revealing
the details what is your North Star and
how has your journey been in terms of
finding mentors and then building the
relationship being of course and you
know in retrospect I actually wish I did
a better job of of defining my north
star from the beginning luckily I still
got to where I am but I didn't really
have a good North Star in the beginning
and one of the reasons was that when I
started my career as an engineer the
concept of separate IC and managerial
tracks wasn't as well defined as it is
today so some companies still had it but
today it's become a de facto standard
every company has a track for individual
contributors and track for managers back
then it didn't really exist so if you
wanted to get promoted and you know I'm
not talking about the very large tech
companies like like Microsoft they
always had this but I'm talking about
most other companies you really had to
become a manager in order to get
promoted and I kind of became a manager
without even realizing that the decision
I want to make so in retrospect I was
lucky because it is what I want to do
but I didn't go through the right
process of defining my North Star once I
did realize that I want to become a
manager and a better manager the first
thing I did was look around me and see
who are the managers that I admire
before doing a good job or who are doing
great job motivating their people who
are delivering at high speeds you know
there are various skills to management
but most importantly you need to as they
say manage down manage up and manage
sideways so thinking through who are the
best managers for each of these three
directions around me and just spending a
lot of time with them and at some point
they sort of become your mentors and
they might be your direct managers as
well but if they're good mentors they
continue to be those even when they're
not your direct managers and this that
happened to me with one of my first
managers and he was my team lead as I
was an engineer and I've learned so much
from him and then I got promoted and we
were actually peers for a while and then
he got promoted and was once again my
manager and I was lucky to have him once
again as the manager and not just as a
mentor but even in between he was always
my mentor and always the the person I
went to seek advice from
great thanks for that
a related question on management so what
are the ways I've been used for
engineering managers to obscale it's a
tough question because as managers first
of all there's
you know for let's say that for every
five Engineers or six or seven or
whatever you're gonna have one manager
so it's just a smaller market and you're
not seeing as much content and tools
geared towards engineering managers so
it's harder to get ahead but the good
thing is that you know being an
engineering manager is kind of like
being a manager outside of engineering
so there are a lot of resources on just
being a good manager generally speaking
and then the second thing I would say I
mentioned earlier managing up down
sideways so we're talking about sideways
and up these are things that I think
engineering is not that different in I
mean it is different but if you know how
to manage sideways and upwards in a good
way you'll know how to do it as as an
engineering manager as well managing
down
is a bit different for engineering and
for all the reasons we discussed earlier
so because of that intrinsic motivation
because Engineers are constantly looking
for ways to upskill
managing down means supporting them on
their growth path
and that means actively helping them
find their North Star and actively
trying to match them with the right
mentors getting the right Tools in their
hands so they can gain experience all of
these things make great engineering
managers
right
turning the perspectives or looking from
the perspective of an individual
contributor how does an individual
contributor have a conversation or
convince his or her manager that you
know they need dedicated learning time
if the manager is not actively promoting
upskilling yeah so first of all if your
manager is not actively promoting
upskilling in many cases it could be
because they're just you know too busy
or have not given this active thought
but they're still very interested in
supporting you on that so you know this
is where you need to take initiative and
have a conversation with them and
explain why this is important and if you
don't manage to convince them
and they're not just not actively
interested in supporting your upskilling
but are actually not interested in
supporting it at all then that might be
a good opportunity to look for a new
manager it doesn't mean leaving the
company that you're in maybe there's
another team within the company that is
going to better support you but
definitely have that conversation most
managers I know would be thrilled if
their team members came up to them
wanting help on their career path and
they would definitely love to do
everything they can to help them so you
know I definitely had points in my
career where I didn't give enough
thoughts to upskilling but whenever
someone came up to me and said oh I
really think we should do this and that
I was very receptive to it and this and
that could be anything from conferences
to books to courses there are so many
things that you can do to bring in
workshops there are a lot of things you
can do and then another thing you want
to look into is whether your company has
a dedicated budget for that so sometimes
it'll be called an lnd budget which
stands for Learning and Development so
you want to understand your company
might have an l d budget per person your
engineering team might have an l d
budget per person so figure out where
that is and in some cases even without
your direct manager's support you might
be able to use that budget towards thing
that things that you appreciate and you
know that means you're going to have to
have better mentors who are going to
help you define what it is that you want
to achieve If your manager is not
supporting you but at least you'll have
the budget to accomplish that and most
engineering teams I know starting from a
certain size definitely at 100 people or
above have some sort of lnd allowance
all right and I think that's a good
segue to our next section which is
talking about engineering managers the
challenges they face and how they can
enable upskilling so talking about the
cost of upskilling how do you justify
the investment and learning and
developments of the lnd budget to upper
management
that's a good point and it's kind of
related to my previous answer so in the
same way that you're talking to your
direct manager and trying to come up
with your upscaling program for you
you're you could assume your direct
manager is having that conversation with
their manager trying to create an
upscaling program for the team and you
know this doubles all the way up now in
companies with large engineering teams
they're usually enough advocates
for upskilling that you as an individual
engineer don't actually have to convince
the company that it's important you just
have to steer the program in your right
direction in the things you want to
achieve if it's a small team you might
have to start from scratch and I would
start with things that don't actually
cost a lot
so if you're a small team you know you
could come up to your manager and say
something like what if we do a weekly
engineering meeting where every week
someone comes up with a topic that they
want to talk to the group about and the
topic could be directly related to
something that happened or is part of
the technology stack or it could be
something completely different that is
somewhat related to what we're doing
and you know that's a great way to start
and for the engineering manager the the
only cost associated with it is the time
allotted for that meeting now I'm not
saying it's a it's a small cost it's
definitely a big one getting all the
engineers in one room for an hour that
is pretty expensive but engineering time
is it works differently than what we
think there's a limit as knowledge
workers there's a limit to how much we
can focus on any given problem in a row
and and that's why you know we like to
say that we don't like context switches
but then if you ask people how they
solved a big problem they'll always say
oh I took a break and did something else
right I thought about it in the shower
so actually taking an hour a week and
just providing that context switch to
people
even if they seem to be super busy can
actually I think be very productive
yeah I've seen quite a lot of companies
have the lunch and learn sessions where
there are informal sessions where
somebody within the company comes in
presence and talks through a new
technology
yeah exactly some people call it lunch
and learn some people call it I've heard
the term brown bag because people bring
the brown bag with the food into the
meeting you know call it whatever you
like but just having that conversation
on a weekly basis and and having people
come up with interesting topics could be
great and it really doesn't have to be
you know related to what we're doing so
back when I was at wework we had those
weekly conversations and people you know
we had someone speak about how they
programmed the microcontroller to
program their Ace to remotely control
their AC unit at home so they can turn
it on before they get home I gave a talk
about how I created this algorithm for
ranking sports groups you know as long
as it's
you know somewhat related to engineering
and could pique your interest in
something new I think it's worth it as
an engineering manager how do you Foster
a culture of Learning and Development
within your team
first and foremost it starts with hiring
one of the things I hire for is
curiosity
because I think curious people are
always advancing or always upskilling
and they tend to it tends to be
contagious so if you're surrounded by a
lot of curious people there's a good
chance that some of it is rubbing off on
you so it starts with hiring sorry if I
can interpret over there
and how do you measure curiosity in an
interview setting it's more art than
science I always say but the key thing
for me is asking them about things
they've done and then trying to push the
boundary of what they're explaining to
me so you know talk about a system that
you've built
is great
but then I would ask them about a
component that they didn't have direct
interaction with and what do they know
about it talk to them through a decision
they've made and as they explain their
pros and cons they're going to figure
out how much they've actually
spent in researching things around it
talk to them about Alternatives that
they've learned after the fact you know
if you would have done it today what
would you have done differently and part
of it is going to be lessons that
they've learned and and another part is
going to be just things unrelated things
that they've picked up along the way and
have changed their view on things so
it's just about finding the right
questions that are
close to what you're talking about but
not directly at it yep very helpful
apologies for interrupting so you
mentioned the first point around
building a culture is hiring yeah some
people say that culture eventually boils
down to who you hire who you fire fire
and who you promote because that kind of
sends the signal on what type of
behavior is appreciated at the company
so definitely hire people who are
Learners that's the first thing the
second thing is showing that you care
and you know that means doing those
lunch and learns or brown bag talks that
means showing that you develop
you know sharing things that you've
picked up with a team when they see that
you've picked up something new and they
know you're super busy right but they
see you pick up something new they say
oh this is great and and if my manager
was able to find the time to pick up new
skills maybe I can do that too so that's
the second thing and then the third
thing and really the the number one tool
I think for managers is always the
one-on-ones with their team members so
during the one-on-one what I like to do
is almost never talk about you know
progress or anything like that you know
there are ways to to give out progress
reports to me one-on-ones are all about
supporting the growth of the person in
front of me
and dedicating the entire conversation
to it
both you know creates the understanding
with them that I am mindful of it that
I'm encouraging them to do that and also
allows us to discuss tactics and figure
out the best ways for them to upskill
right to summarize the first one that
you should focus on is hiring and if you
give that right you don't need to do the
firing the second one is around caring
for your team members career progression
and growth and the last one is having
quality one-on-ones yeah and also
leading by example
okay we have a session on software
engineering radio around one to one
where we do a deep dive on on that topic
with without drop era and make sure we
have a link to that in this session in
the show notes what are some strategies
you use to identify skill gaps within
your teams that is a really hard one so
first of all we'll start by saying that
many of the skills in engineering are
not measurable in an easy way right so
some other functions in the organization
there's some other disciplines might be
easier to measure and the classics a
classic example is always sales
eventually there's a result and it's
easy to measure sales people buy it
whereas with engineering you know even
though in one aspect we're the most
scientific part of the organization but
when it comes to measurements we're
actually the least scientific part of it
so it's really hard to measure and this
is where good managers have to shine and
eventually
subjective reporting is as an important
tool is everything as anything else in
this regard so the ability of a team
lead to say we're missing out on this
skill set and being able to escalate
that or the ability of a VP of
engineering to say or understaffed
on database expertise we really need to
hire for this or really need to train
people on this
you know it really needs to Bubble up
for that to succeed however there are
tools to help you map this out and you
know there are tools that would try to
extract things from your code base and a
lot of the l d tools one of the things
they'll try to do is map out the various
skill sets that people have and then you
know present a sort of a centralized
report so it doesn't have to be on on
the specific individual it's more
aggregated the skills that you have in
the team the skills that are progressing
in the team
Etc but eventually there's no
replacement
to you know bubbling this information up
the chain from the individual and you
know the more honest they could be with
themselves the better off they'll be and
the easier it is for them to to progress
and then all the way up to the VP of
engineering right also in the context of
upskilling as an engineering manager how
do you balance the Need For Engineers to
work on current projects with the need
for the upskill for the future so you
know how do you balance the short-term
demands with a long-term development of
your team
yeah it's always a tricky balance and I
want to go back to what I said earlier
about engineers time working a bit
differently so I mentioned that
Engineers are actually looking for
context switches you know even though
they say that they aren't and they hate
it they actually they actually need it
you could say it's a necessary evil
Engineers actually I believe have a
limit to the number of productive hours
they can contribute in a day
and if they're in the office or it
doesn't have to be in the office you
know it could be remote but if they're
actively working for eight hours they're
most likely not working on production
code for eight hours they're doing a lot
of other things as well and one of those
things I think or one of the most
important things I think should be
investing in their upskilling and
they're you know within those eight
hours a day there's actually a lot of
time to fit in a lot of different things
maybe they're waiting on a code review
maybe they just need some context switch
to solve a problem that they've been
banging their head against the wall with
maybe they completed a very difficult
task they need some time off the cool
thing is that upskilling actually lets
you
use up your time in a very effective way
while still clearing your head so you
know if I finish something big I can go
on social media and that's probably not
going to be very productive but you know
that's sort of a pause that I need but
then if I instead of going on social
media I use that pause
for professional development that I've
achieved two goals in one I was able to
get that pause and get that contact
switch but it also became productive so
find Avenues where your people can spend
you know 30 minutes on something that's
going to help their professional growth
that's one the second thing is I
mentioned earlier that in a way we're
still an apprenticeship kind of
profession and that means that whenever
you're progressing there is a good
chance that there's someone a bit more
senior than you who's also spending
active time on that progression if I can
support you on your growth path without
needing another human in the picture
then I've actually freed up time rather
than taking up time and that really
helps you know as you're talking about
the balance between investing in now and
investing in the future if that future
investment is actually saving the time
now then it becomes a no-brainer right
agreed we talked about culture earlier
and I just wanted to understand how does
that operate in the current environment
where most of the teams are operating
either in a hybrid fashion or where you
have remote or distributed teams
are there some strategies to ensure that
the remote teams also are part of that
same culture and feel equally involved
yeah remote remote is very tricky in
that sense one of the things that's
really missing
with remote is the ability to tap
someone on the shoulder
and ask for advice
and it's hard to do remotely so the you
know the first thing I would do is
figure out some social Norm within your
company that's the equivalent of tapping
on the shoulder if it's across time
zones it becomes more complicated but
hopefully you can find the people in
your time zone or at least in
overlapping in an overlapping time zone
that you can have that tap on the
shoulder moment with that's the first
thing the second thing is
as you're picking up skills one of the
most difficult things is what we call
the unknown unknowns right these are the
things that you should pick up and you
don't know about
so the better that the knowledge is
preserved within your organization the
ability for people to find things that
they they didn't even know that they
need to know the more you can support
the culture of upskilling so you know
let's say that when I joined the on-call
rotation in the team one of the biggest
uh or most frequent things I'll tackle
would be some admin interface that acts
weirdly every time now if I don't know
that I need to learn about it then I'm
going to be unprepared for my on-call
shift but if there's a good knowledge
base of the things most likely to break
when you're on call then you know I know
what to look for and I can pick up those
skills that I need to be ready to feel
that when it does happen right any
examples where firms have implemented a
good social Norm for that tap on
shoulder for remote teams how do they do
it yeah this could be a dedicated slack
Channel where you um you know you could
even call it a tap on the shoulder
Channel and people join it when they're
ready to be interrupted and then someone
can just you know come into this the
channel and seek seek advice when they
need it so that's that's one way I've
seen this work in the beginning when you
know beginning with you know a few years
ago when people started exploring with
how remote works I've seen teams that
are constantly on video with each other
and you know when you do that you feel a
bit more comfortable virtually tapping
someone on the shoulder because you're
also looking at them I have to admit I'm
not a huge fan of that feels a bit weird
to me to be in an office like that so
definitely finding the async ways of
doing that use your corporate chat to
your advantage but also keep in mind
that as everything async it means that
it becomes you know eventually
consistent but not necessarily
immediately so if you're tapping someone
on the shoulder over a chat you might
actually get a response you know an hour
later or maybe six hours later and
that's why it's important to have things
that you can context switch into while
you're waiting for that and and that
goes again to why I think that upscaling
doesn't really take time because there
are so many opportunities for you to
pick up other things as you're waiting
on on things I wanted to talk about a
challenge that engineering managers
sometimes run into which is the
resistance to change so some employees
May resist upskilling especially if they
feel that a current skills and
experiences are sufficient for for the
present job or the current job how do
you you know talk to them and tell them
that the new skills and Technologies
though not immediately relevant
could you know will help them in the
future how do you address this problem
or how do you have that conversation
with such employees or team members
yeah first of all you need to go into
this understanding that
there's only so much you can do to
influence other people and If eventually
they don't see upskilling as an
important investment for them
there's a good chance you might not
convince them the easiest way to
convince them is through culture I
mentioned earlier you know who you hire
who you fire who you promote if they see
everyone around them investing in their
in their skill set and getting promoted
while they're staying in place
then that could have an impact on them
right that could be actions speak louder
than words and if I'm seeing that I'm
not investing anything in my
professional growth and I'm the only one
around that's staying in place there's a
good chance I'm going to get convinced I
would also share my history you know
situations where I was able to leverage
seemingly unrelated skills or you know
talk to them about stories of people
with similar concerns about upskilling
that eventually you did invest in their
upskilling and you know the things they
were able to achieve achieve but I think
the trickiest
situations are with the Busy Bee types
you know these are people who are always
busy and they just can't seem to find a
time to anything to do anything and and
you know the first thing you want to do
with them is help them with time
management skills and once you do that
they you know not only get more time but
they also realize how skills that aren't
directly related to their job can also
be very beneficial
so you know figure out who is the best
time management expert around and and
bring them in for a conversation and I
think sometimes it's a reflection of the
environment you're operating in so if
you're if your team is constantly
firefighting that means you don't have
time for upskilling so maybe you need to
look at how do you create that time to
bring stability and resilience into your
product or environment
absolutely
moving on to the next section which is
around measurement we've already touched
on it previously but digging a bit
deeper into it how do you measure the
return on investment on upskilling
efforts yeah you know once again going
back to what I said about those things
not being very easily measurable the
best place to start is self-reported and
when I say self-reported that means the
person in their direct manager you know
if I'm saying I feel like I'm behind on
skills a b and c but I'm really getting
ahead on skills d e and f and I can do
it in an honest fashion
and then my team lead can also give me
pointers and say something like you know
what
I think you're actually too hard on
yourself with skill a I think you're
doing okay B and C you're right you're
you need to pick up the pace D that you
thought is going well well you know I'd
actually like to see you do better and
enf are really doing great so the
synthesis of you and your direct manager
should go a long way towards measuring
the team now if you're talking about a
larger team and not just the individual
then
and you you can start looking at sort of
all sorts of proxy metrics so let's say
that there is an infrastructure team at
your company and when something breaks
in the infrastructure you open a support
ticket
what you can do is
figure out how people are learning the
infrastructure or getting better skills
with that infrastructure by looking at
the number of tickets and as it goes
down you know assuming the
infrastructure stays the same if the
number of tickets tickets go down it's a
good assault you know it's good
assumption to make that people are
better trained with it right so that
could be an objective metric if training
is happening during onboarding you can
measure the time it takes for people to
become productive or you know their
contributions in the first few months or
the number of bugs they put into
production in the first few months each
of those by itself
is not a good metric because it's easy
to aim and it's easy to put too much
weight into meaningless things but a
combination of many of these could be a
good way to measure things so be very
context sensitive and figure out the
proxy metrics that are going to provide
the more objective measure and and use
that to balance the subjective measure
of the individuals and their team leads
got it it's a difficult problem but one
has to keep the context in mind and use
various proxy measures to get a holistic
picture yeah exactly and any thoughts in
terms of
how do you keep track of the
capabilities of your team because as
people obscure the skills are going to
change you know you could have hired a
t-shaped developer who quickly becomes
Pi shape or comb shaped has develops and
learns those skills
and how do you keep track of that
capabilities
yeah it's a great question and this is
where I think it's first and foremost on
the team lead level to notice these
things and notice who's picking up new
skills but also
who's losing skills right because
there's a good chance that has your as
you're picking up new skills you might
be losing some of the others that you're
not exercising as often so it's really
up to the team lead to find a balance
and and as they bubble it up all the way
to the VP of engineering then they have
to look at the organization as a whole
and make decisions based on that but
each level really needs to have a skill
map
of the various skills on the team which
ones are progressing which ones are
declining which ones are going to need
the need more work in essence I would
say it's an exercise in good management
yep agreed in the last section I'd like
to close off the show talking about
what's in the future how we have already
you know you've touched on low code no
code also about AI but how do you
identify which emerging Technologies are
most relevant to your team and to your
business
well first of all you know it's really
hard in Hebrew we like to say that
prophecy is a Fool's errand and we've
all made you know really really bad
forecasts so we have to be very careful
and I think the trick is to invest the
minimum amount required in a given piece
of technology to figure out if you need
to invest more in it right sort of like
a pyramid where at the bottom you invest
the very minimum you need to understand
and at the top this is a skill or a
technology that you want to spend a lot
of time on some companies might create
some shortcuts for you you know there
are a lot of Technology Radars out there
that would talk about the emerging
Technologies and which ones you should
be adopting and which ones you might
actually should be dropping
and you also want to listen to your
people so I mentioned earlier about
hiring curious people there's a good
chance those curious people are going to
spend time even their sometimes their
free time looking through new
technologies trying to figure out which
ones are right fit for the team I know
that when I was an engineer I came to my
team lead quite a lot with you know this
is really interesting what if we try
this or this is really interesting I
don't think there's anything we can do
with it right now but it's definitely
something to keep in mind for the future
so trusting your people sending them out
there to pick up things you know whether
it's through conferences or through just
reading and then trusting their judgment
to bring the right types of Technologies
back to you I think you also want to
balance this with some top-down thinking
too though so you know especially if we
look at a company like Wilco
we also need to think not just which
Technologies are relevant for us but
because of what we do we need to think
through which Technologies are going to
be relevant to engineering teams in
general and that requires kind of a
balance of not just individuals coming
up with ideas but also more conservative
thinking and trying to identify major
themes in the industry what is your firm
doing in the upscreening space
so Wilco you can think of it kind of
like a flight simulator but for software
instead of for Aviation so we let
developers join a fantasy company and
that company has a production-like
system with logging and monitoring and
analytics and load balancing and a real
data set but more importantly it also
has colleagues that would be virtual
colleagues and team leads and product
managers and support people and on top
of that you go on simulations of real
world scenarios so this could be
something like hey we have a performance
problem in production please figure out
what happened what's the root cause
what's the extent of the damage fix it
and communicate at the stakeholders so
we do that and the focus is not on the
Fix-It part which is more the
theoretical aspect of it of things you
know I spoke earlier about the need to
balance Theory and hands-on experience
but for us when you go through something
like this we want you to focus on how do
you even know that something went wrong
in production what do you do to
investigate it when do you go for a
quick and dirty fix when do you go for
something more meaningful how do you
ensure that lessons are learned and
implemented all these little things that
we pick up throughout our career and
make up our experience that's a very
interesting approach to upskilling and
who's your primary target audience
so we have a free version that anyone
can sign up to and play quests from
within our catalog and you know these
are quests that we've written but also
quests contributed by the community you
know anyone can also build their own
scenarios on top of Wilco and also
quests built by our partners we have
Partners such as do Relic and circle CI
and Docker and and a few others so you
can play all this content for free and
then companies that want to invest in
upscaling their teams can get the
business edition of the product that's
going to give them way more features and
the ability to create their own custom
Quests for internal use connect their
own code base so that the quest can run
on top of the platforms that they want
to deal with and also get the reporting
which you know goes into many of the
questions you asked me earlier about how
do I know which skills I have on the
team and which ones are in need so
getting that report from Wilco can
really help you get the answers you need
for that no completely agree I think you
know you have so many firms going
through a transformation journey and the
challenges you implement the new product
but you have no idea how it's going to
be supported or is it being trained
enough to be able to support it post go
live so I think Wilco you know the
product over here will be a good
addition to ensure to give that Comfort
to stakeholders business and technology
that the team is ready to support in
postcode live yeah definitely and you
know this is both for for just the
generic upskilling of your team and
everything we discussed today and also
for more specific scenarios like you
know helping someone join the on-call
rotation or boarding someone new picking
up a new piece of tech or maybe you've
switched from one very to another
eventually there are a lot of events
within the life cycle of an engineer
that requires an investment in their
skills
we covered a lot of ground here but if
there is one thing a software engineer
should remember from the entire session
what would it be I would say two things
first own your career path figure out
your North Star where you want to be and
invest in it if like I said earlier if
you're not moving ahead you're getting
behind and the second thing is remember
it's eventually it's a people's
profession find the right mentors invest
in your soft skills the ability to get
along with people on the team is way
more important than any line of code
completely agree was there anything we
missed that you'd like to mention I
think we covered quite a lot this was
very comprehensive thanks on people can
follow you on Twitter but how else can
people get in touch sure well first of
all my DM is open so they can they can
just ping me on Twitter
if you're playing Wilco you can always
use our intercom or any of our support
channels to reach out and also you know
share your feedback we love that too and
looking forward to hearing what you know
everyone thinks about our product and
and the type of progress they've had and
if in any way impacted your career
that's definitely something we'd love to
hear thank you for coming on the show
it's been a real pleasure this is
brijesh Amanda for software engineering
radio thank you for listening thank you
pleasure was all mine
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se.radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under created Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening
thank you
foreign